Guide to the Erasmus Club Records, 1926-1986
Duke University. University Archives
Erasmus Club records 1926-1986
Duke University. University Archives
Duke University. Erasmus Club.
1.5 linear feet Extent: approx. 1,000 Items
The Erasmus Club was a campus literary society which organized in 1926 for the encouragement of study and research in language and literature, and later, the humanities in general. The collection contains minutes, correspondence, memoranda, students' essays, financial records, announcements and other material. It ranges in date from 1926-1986.
UA.28.01.0002
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Collection is open for research.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
The Erasmus Club Records were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1964 and 1982.
Historical Note
The Erasmus Club was a campus literary society which organized in 1926 for the encouragement of study and research in language and literature, and later, the humanities in general. It was sometimes called the Erasmus Philology Club. Membership was open to faculty members and to those recommended by faculty. The club sponsored readings and other presentations and usually met annually with the Philological Club of the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill.
Beginning in 1943, the Erasmus Club awarded a prize for the best undergraduate essay in the humanities. Winners included Reynolds Price (1954) and Fred Chappell (1961). The Club was dissolved in 1986 due to a lack of interest.
Collection Overview
The collection includes minutes, correspondence, memoranda, students' essays, financial records, announcements and other material. There are scattered lists of speakers and topics, of joint meetings with the faculty of UNC, and of papers submitted. The minutes for the period of 1926-1938 are in a bound volume which also includes correspondence, notes and newspaper clippings. Minutes for 1938-1960 are loose and arranged chronologically by academic year, although there are some gaps. Scattered minutes for later years can be found in the Secretary's files. Student essays submitted for the prize make up half the collection. Where known, the winning entry and runner-up are arranged chronologically. The remainder are arranged alphabetically by the author's last name. The material ranges in date from 1926-1986.
Subject Headings
Duke University. Erasmus Club; Duke University -- Faculty -- History; Duke University -- Societies, etc.; Duke University. Erasmus Philology Club; Price, Reynolds, 1933-; Chappell, Fred, 1936-
Related Material
Columbian and Hesperian Literary Society Records
Duke University Archives
Faculty Reference Collection
Duke University Archives
Faculty Records
Duke University Archives
Faculty Club Records
Duke University Archives
Contents of Collection
- Container List
  - Minutes, 1926-1938 (Box 1)
  - Minutes, 1938/39-1944/45
  - Minutes, 1945/46-1959/60
  - Secretary
  - Secretary, lists of meetings
  - Secretary, 1926-1929
  - Secretary, 1930-1939
  - Secretary, 1940-1949
  - Secretary, financial, 1948-1949
  - Secretary, 1949/50-1953/54
  - Secretary, 1954/55-1955/56
  - Secretary, 1956/57-1959/60
  - Secretary, 1960-1969
  - Secretary, 1969-1979
  - Secretary, 1979-1980
  - Secretary, 1985-1986
  - Announcements
  - Prize Lists, 1946-1958, notes
  - Essays, Prize Winning, 1942, 1944, 1946, 1949, 1950
  - Essays, Prize Winning, 1951, 1954, 1958, 1961, 1962
  - Essays, Prize Winning, 1964-1965
  - Essays, Author A-B
  - Essays, Author C-F
  - Essays, Author G-H
  - Essays, Author, J-M
  - Essays, Author N-R
  - Essays, Author S-T
  - Essays, Author W-Z